Ok, so let's look at some ways to actually get tasks done.
One way to make things happen is to use the command line of the zos-unix directory list
panel.
You can enter commands such as edit to edit a file in a directory that's currently listed,
find will find and display the next occurrence of a character string within the list of
file names, reset cleans up the directory list display by removing pending line commands
and messages and so forth.
The following line commands are available on the zos-unix directory list panel.
You can enter these line commands alongside the file you'd like to apply the command
to.
So, if you want to rename a file, you'd enter the r line command alongside the file
you want to rename.
These line commands result in panels being displayed.
Let's take a look.
The create new zos-unix file panel allows a user to create a file and is invoked using
the n line command.
The user must enter the path name and permissions for the new file and identify the file type.
When creating a symbolic or an external link, the user must identify the file the link
refers to.
Options are available to have data copied from another file or data set into the new
file and to edit the new file.
The sticky bit can also be set on for the new file.
The copy from panel allows the data from a file to be copied to another file or to
a sequential data set or member of a partition data set and it's invoked using
the co-line command against a regular file.
The user must specify the name of the target zos-unix file or sequential data set or partition
data set and member.
When the data is to be copied to a zos-unix file, the user can specify the permissions
for this file.
The following options are available.
You can be warned if the data is being copied to a target that exists.
When the target isn't an existing zos-unix file, you can have its permissions updated.
You can cause a binary copy to occur when copying to a sequential data set or member.
And you can cause data conversion to take place during the copy operation where an
optional conversion table can be specified.
The copy from panel allows the data from regular files in a directory to be copied to
two members in a partition data set and it's invoked using the co-line command against
the directory.
The user must specify the name of the target partition data set and the following options
are available.
Data in existing members can be overridden with the data from the source file.
A selection list can be displayed where the user can select the files in the directory
that are to be copied.
File names with names containing lowercase characters can be copied.
Files with names containing suffixes can be copied by having the suffix removed.
A binary copy can occur when copying to the target member and as with files, data conversion
can take place during the copy operation.
The replace panel allows the data in a regular zos-unix file to be replaced with data from
another file or replaced with the sequential data set or a member of a partition data set.
The user must specify the name of the source zos-unix file, sequential data set or partition
data set and member and the following options are available for this.
A binary copy can occur when copying from a sequential data set or a member and, yep,
we can do data conversion.
The copy into panel allows the data from members in a partition data set to be copied
into regular files in a directory and that's invoked using the ci line command against a directory.
The user must specify the name of the source partition data set and the user can specify
the permissions to apply to the files the members are copied into.
The user can also specify a suffix which is appended to the member name to make the
name of the regular file created or updated during the copy operation and the usual array
of options are available.
The file information panel displays the attributes for a file or a directory and is invoked using
the i line command.
The modify pull down menu contains options to modify either the mode fields or the extended
attributes for the file.
The modify mode panel allows the user to change the permissions, set uid bit, set gid
bit and the sticky bit all for a file.
It's invoked using the mm line command or using the modify pull down menu on the zos
unix file information panel.
The execute command panel allows the user to run a file or execute a zos unix command,
a tso command, C list or rex exec against a file.
It's invoked using the x line command against a regular file, directory or symbolic link
to a regular file.
For a command that runs in zos unix, the user has the option to run the command under the
login shell or directly in zos unix.
To simply run the selected file, the user can leave the command for the file field blank.
By default, the path name of the selected file is appended to the end of the command
entered by the user.
The panel here shows a request to run the C 89 command to compile, assemble and link
edit a C program.
The command is run in the zos unix login shell.
Next up, we'll take a look at how zos unix works with ispf and for that, I'll see you
back at the office.